Nancy L. Johnson Papers 2007.0008
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Nancy L. Johnson Papers
undated, 1983-2006.
2007.0008
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
222.3 Linear feet
The papers of Congresswoman Nancy Lee Johnson. A member of the Connecticut state senate (1977-1982) and delegate to the Republican National Convention in 1980, Ms. Johnson was elected as a Republican to the Ninety-eighth and to the eleven succeeding Congresses (January 3, 1983-January 3, 2007). Ms. Johnson was a Republican member of the United States House of Representatives from 1983 to 2007, representing first the 6th district and later the 5th District of Connecticut following the elimination of the 6th district.
Johnson, Nancy Lee, 1935-
Biography
Nancy Lee Johnson was born in Chicago, Illinois. She graduated from the University of Chicago Laboratory School (1953) and from Radcliffe College (1957). She attended the University of London's Courtauld Institute in 1957 and 1958.
Ms. Johnson began her political career as a Senator in the Connecticut General Assembly from 1977-1982. In 1982, Ms. Johnson was elected to the U.S. House of Representatives, defeating Democrat William E. Curry, Jr.. She replaced Democrat Anthony Moffett ("Toby"), who made an unsuccessful bid for the U.S. Senate that year. In 2002, Johnson's New Britain-based district was merged with the Waterbury-based 5th District of Democratic Congressman Jim Maloney.
The most senior woman in the U.S. House of Representatives in the 109th Congress, she is a recognized authority on health policy. Ms. Johnson's legislative accomplishments include a variety of matters related to health care, children, taxes, manufacturing and the environment. She co-authored the national Children's Health Insurance Program, was a principal author of the Medicare Modernization Act and authored several taxpayer rights bills as Chairman of the Oversight Subcommittee. As a senior member of the House Ways and Means Committee and a free-trade proponent, Ms. Johnson played an integral role in passage of every major tax bill, trade agreement and health care initiative during her tenure on the committee.
Representative Johnson was the first Republican woman to be appointed to the powerful House Ways and Means Committee and also the first woman to chair one of its subcommittees. As a member and chairman of the Health Subcommittee, Ms. Johnson co-authored the laws that expanded Medicare to cover prescription drugs, chronic care management, increased preventive health benefits, and care offered by nurse specialists, physician assistants and nutritionists. She also introduced the health information technology legislation that led to the establishment of the Office of the National Coordinator for Health Information Technology (HIT) and fought for broad adoption of HIT to reduce medical errors and improve care quality. She also led the Long Term Care Coalition, was an avid supporter of Community Health Centers and children's hospitals, and worked to pass malpractice reform and mental health parity legislation.
Throughout her service on the committee, she co-authored many reforms of our pension laws, creating the Simple Plan for small businesses, many tax incentives to encourage personal savings and passage of the landmark Portman-Cardin reform and the Pension Protection Act of 2006, which together broadened pension participation significatnly. In the 109th Congress she changed the tax treatment of annuity payments when directed to long term care facilities, creating a new and more flexible option for long term care coverage.
In support of manufacturing and small business, Congresswoman Johnson focused on tax incentives to invest: increasing expensing for small business, modernizing depreciation law to support high tech manufacturing, authoring the alternative research and development credit to support product development by startups and reformed the low income housing tax credit to improve affordable housing options. She was a consistent advocate for the federal program that assists small manufacturers in improving quality and productivity and of lower tax rates to maintain entrepreneurial vitality.
Representing a trading state, Ms. Johnson introduced and worked for passage of trade negotiating authority, agreements expanding market access and laws strengthening enforcement of intellectual property rights, anti-dumping and other fair trade initiatives. She worked to increase funding for Department of Commerce export promotion and support services and for the Foreign Commercial Service, and was a strong support of the EX-IM Bank. She provided extensive constituent services to those needing to be heard by the USTR or other federal agencies and worked closely with companies to better inform their employees regarding trade, tax, and other issues affecting their competitiveness and future.
As chairman of the Human Resources Subcommittee, Ms. Johnson improved foster care programs, and expanded the Independent Living Program to support teenagers aging out of foster care and transitioning to college or work. She championed health and child care benefits for families leaving public assistance and led the adoption of much stronger laws to enforce child support responsibilities. She early understood the danger to children of sex predators on the internet and led passage of increased funding and better law enforcement tools to apprehend internet sex predators.
As the chairman of the Oversight Subcommittee, she authored a series of taxpayer rights bills that provided protections for individuals and small businesses and implemented the recommendations of the commission to reorganize the IRS to modernize consumer services and enhance agency accountability.
Ms. Jonson currently is a senior public policy advisor in Washington, D.C., office and focuses on health care, tax and trade matters.
Professional Honors & Activities
2007 Fellow – Institute of Poitemtics at Harvard University
2006 Artic Refuge Congressional Champion Award – The Audubon Society
2006 Leadership Award – eHEALTH Connecticut
2006 Visiting Nurses Association Award for Patience and Tenacity in Support of Homecare
2005 Edgar Wayburn Award – Sierra Club
2005 Legislator of the Year Award – The American College of Physicians
2004 Hero of the Taxpayer Award – Americans for Tax Reform
2004 Special Merit Award, Manufacturing Advocate of the Year Award – CONNSTEP
2003 Alfred B. Lewis President's Award – Disease Management Association of America
2003 R.J. Corletta Award for Achievement in Affordable Housing
2002 The Mary Eitemza Mahoney Award – National Minority Health Month
2002 Circle of Excellence Award – The Latino Coaitemtion
2002 President's Recognition Award – National PTA
2000 Government Leadership in the Arts Award – American's for the Arts
1998 Outstanding Women in International Trade – Association of Women in International Trade
1996 Outstanding Service Award – Community Action Agencies and Programs and Head Start
1994 Dr. Nathan Davis Award for Outstanding Pubitemc Service – American Medical Association
Spirit of Enterprise – National Chamber of Commerce – Received repeatedly
National Federation of Independent Businessmen ( NFIB) – Received repeatedly
Honorary Degrees
Baypath College, Honorary Degree, Doctor of Humane Letters, 1999
University of New Haven, Doctor of Laws, Honoris Causa, 1995
University of Hartford, Doctor of Laws, 1989
University of Bridgeport, Honorary Degree, Doctor of Humane Letters, 1985
Scope and Contents
The papers of Congresswoman Nancy Lee Johnson. The collection contains floor and committee statements, correspondence, speeches, reports, studies, bills, schedules, awards, photographs, videoes and campaign materials documenting Ms. Johnson's career in the U.S. House of Representatives.
Arrangement
The boxes have been numbered and inventoried as they are currently shelved.
Inventory ( undated, 1983-2006 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to Connecticut politics. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The following materials have been separated from the collection and cataloged:
The Hartford Club 'Women Who Dare' Series with former congresswomen Barbara Kennelly and Nancy Johnson DVD 107
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Acquisition Information
The majority of the materials were donated by Ms. Johnson in January and April 2007. Additional materials were added in October 2007.
Johnson, Nancy Lee, 1935-; Administrative Records.; Audio cassettes.; Correspondence.; Financial Records.; Fliers. [printed matter]; Minutes.; Notebooks.; Notes.; Photocopies.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Publications.; Speeches.; Videocassettes.; Women legislators--Connecticut--Biography.
- Inventory, undated, 1983-2006
  - Russia, China, Ukraine, undated (Box 1)
  - Interns, Correspondence, undated (Box 2)
  - Schedules, undated (Box 3)
  - Schedules, 1995-1998 (Box 4)
  - Campaign, undated (Box 5)
  - Fathers Bill, Child welfare, Child support, Immigrants, undated (Box 6)
  - Awards, undated (Box 7)
  - Foster care, Pro-Choice, HIPPA, undated (Box 8)
  - Press releases, undated (Box 9)
  - Schedules, 1999-2000 (Box 10)
  - Schedules, 1987-1994 (Box 11)
  - Hungary, Poland, Aspen Institute, Kuwait, Qatar, undated (Box 12)
  - Schedules, 2005 March - 2006 November (Box 13)
  - Schedules, undated (Box 14)
  - Schedules, 2003 (Box 15)
  - Issues, Accomplishments, undated (Box 16)
  - Mark up/Hearing binders, undated (Box 17)
  - Early issue files, undated (Box 18)
  - Welfare reform, undated (Box 19)
  - Press releases, 1997-1999 (Box 20)
  - Aspen Institute, undated (Box 21)
  - Aspen Institute, Briefing book, Indonesia, undated (Box 22)
  - Schedules, undated (Box 23)
  - HR, 1985 (Box 24)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 25)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 26)
    - McAdams - McZ
    - Mar - Maz
    - Ma - Map
    - Mick - Mil
    - Min - Mor
    - Mos - Mz
    - Na - Ne
    - Ni - Nz
    - Oa - One
    - Ong - Oz
    - Pa = Patt
    - pau - Pf
    - Ph - Pol
  - Project Excell, undated (Box 27)
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 28)
  - Meeting files, undated (Box 29)
  - Invitations, 1985 (Box 30)
  - Issue files, undated (Box 31)
  - Form letters, undated (Box 32)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 33)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 34)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 35)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 36)
  - HR, 1987 (Box 37)
  - Form letters, undated (Box 38)
  - Conferences, undated (Box 39)
  - Israel, Journal, Gibbons Codel, undated (Box 40)
  - Votes and Bills, 19893-1987 (Box 41)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 42)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 43)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 44)
  - Issues/Correspondence, undated (Box 45)
  - Binders of Sample letters, undated
  - Binders of Press releases, undated
  - Correspondence, 1983 (Box 46)
    - Pa - Pd
    - Pe - Pi
    - Pl
    - Po - Pz
    - Q
    - Ra - Rd
    - Re - Rh
    - Ri - Rn
    - Ro - Rt
    - Ru - Rz
    - Sa - Sb
    - Sca - Scz
    - Sd - Sh
    - Si - Sl
    - Sm - Sn
    - So - Ss
    - St
    - Su - Sz
    - Ta - Tg
    - Th - Tr
    - Ts - Tz
    - Ua - Uz
    - Va - Vi
    - Vj - Vz
    - Wa
    - Wf - Wh
    - Wi - Wn
    - Wo - Wz
    - Ya - Yz
    - Za - Zm
    - Zn - Zz
  - Files, undated, 1995-2001 (Box 47)
    - Patients' Bill of Rights (PBR)
    - Subcommittee on Health, Hearing on Patient Protections in Managed Care, 2001
    - EITC, 1995
    - Taxpayer Bill of Rights, 1997-1998
    - Oversight subcommittee, 1995-1996
    - Oversight file, Tax simplification
    - Oversight subcommittee
      - Land use, 1997 July
      - Small Business, June 1998
      - Debt collection, 1997 May
  - HR Files, 1984 (Box 48)
  - Files, undated (Box 49)
  - Votes and Bills, undated (Box 50)
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986, 2005 (Box 51)
    - Sa - Sca
    - Sch - See
    - Sef - Shee
    - Shef - Shz
    - Si - Sin
    - Sip - Sk
    - SIRKIN
    - Sl - Spr
    - St - Ste
    - Sti - Sz
    - Ta - Term
    - 2005 February 10 - 16
    - 2005 February 17 -23
    - 2005 Feburary 24 - March 2
    - 2005 March 3 - 9
    - 2005 March 10 - 16
    - 2005 March 17 - 23
    - 2005 March 24 - 30
    - 2005 March 31 - April 5
    - 2005 April 6 - 12
    - 2005 April 13 - 19
    - 2005 April 20 - 26
    - 2005 April 27 - May 2
  - Files, 1983-1986 (Box 52)
    - Newpaper request, 1983
    - David's meeting with Town officials, 1983
    - Chamber of Commerce, 1983
    - Invite to Republican Members, 1983
    - Job Retraining hearing, 1983
    - Springfield meeting, 1983
    - Campaign ephemera, 1983
    - Small Business Conference, 1983
    - Round Table and Thanks, 1983
    - Congrats to State Central Committee, 1983
    - LBJ Teacher Intern, Update, 1984
    - Immigration reform, 1985
    - Flat Tax (Update), 1985
    - Lupus Invite, 1986
    - Medicare Payment Increase, 1986
    - Informed Consent Petitions, 1986
    - NLN Accreditation, 1986
    - Medicare Reimburse for Cataract Surgery, 1986
    - Campaign Finance Reform--Pro, 1984
    - Medicare--Responsiveness Issues (Update), 1986
    - Medicare Pre-Certification, 1986
    - ERA and Abortion, 1984
    - Medicare cuts--Con, 1984
    - Health Fraud, 1984
    - Silent Scream response, 1985
    - Medicare for Digestive Diseases, 1985
    - Blepharaspasm Awareness Week, 1985
    - Medicare cuts (Seniors) update, 1985
  - Files, 1984-1988 (Box 53)
    - Central America--Con
    - Catastrophic Long-Term Care, " Claude Pepper"
    - Handgun Waiting period
    - Generic Drug bill
    - Tax Guide for Seniors
    - Pro-COLA cuts
  - Votes and Bills, 1986 (Box 54)
  - Votes and Bills, 1984 (Box 55)
  - Files, undated, 1985-1986, 1995 (Box 56)
    - Photographs--Interns (Weicker, McKinney, Johnson)
    - Questionnaires
    - Legislative proposal column
    - Publications
    - Block trip--Meeting on farms
    - Federalism--who makes the decisions?
    - Flood Assistance
    - Franco-American Veterans
    - General revenue sharing
    - Grace Commission report
    - Grenada- Lebanon
    - HCFA letter
    - Health care alternatives
    - Health insurance for the unemployed
    - 40th anniversary of Hiroshima
    - Homebased Careers for Women
    - House rules column
    - I-91 - Windsor Highway repairs
    - Illiteracy column
    - IMF
    - Second inaugural address
    - Industrial development bonds
    - Internship programs
    - IRS toll-free number
    - Interstate cost estimates
    - Jobless Benefits extension
    - Jobs bill -- September
    - Jobs task force
    - Jobs--Cooperation, Middle Street park
    - Kansas trip
    - Kissinger Commission
    - Ku Klux Klan rally
    - Lebanon - War Powers Act resolution
    - Martin Luther King
    - Math/Science fair
    - Victoria Mazzarelli
    - Medicare Solvent
    - Mining Nicaragua harbors -- Tax bill
    - Mortgage revenue bonds
    - Mt. Pleasant Housing application
    - New Milford mudslide -- Montes
    - MX Vote reaction
    - Machine tool import limit petition 232
    - Newington Veterans Hospital
    - Republican State Central Newsletter
    - Hazardous wate -- Superfund bill
    - Bridge Inspection information to NTSB
    - Immigration bill
    - Nuclear freeze
    - Olympics--Soviet withdrawal
    - Tip O'Neill letter
    - Pay equity
    - Women's Pension reform
    - Pratt & Whitney
    - Pre-retirement conferences
    - Press Club speech
    - Press
    - Press breakfast
    - Procurement conference
    - Public office hours
    - Public works job bill
    - Public works subcommittee
    - Recess over column
    - Rehab tax credit
    - Retraining hearing
    - Road letter to Burns (ConnDOT)
    - Road repair to small towns -- Clean Water Act
    - SBIR Symposium
    - Schools recognized
    - Select committee on Hunger column
    - Semiconductor Chip bill
    - Seniors
    - Senior intern program
    - Seniority on committees
    - White House conference on Small business
    - 50th anniversary of Social Security
    - Social Security disability
    - Southington landfill
    - Soviety mail intervention
    - Soviet bombing of KAL 007
    - Spending bill -- Trade and export bill
    - Springfield Sewage Dumping situation
    - State of the Union
    - Star Wars debate
    - Statistics and ratings
    - Student loan requirements
    - Substance abuse prevention
    - Substate triggers--unemployment compensation
    - Tampering with testimony
    - Tandem trailers
    - Tax Cap
    - Tax cut and indexing
    - Tax reform
    - Teacher in Space
    - Trade policy changes needed, Business-High Ed Forum, Arizona
    - Teachers-Professional Development conference
    - Teen suicide column
    - Talcott Mountain Satellite broadcast
    - Town meeting card
    - Town meetings
    - Trade partnership act
    - Swearing ceremony
    - Cr - Cz
    - Da - Day
    - De - Di
  - Constituent Correspondence, undated (Box 57)
  - HR, 1985 (Box 58)
  - Correspondence, Voting Record, Itinerary, undated (Box 59)
  - Office Expense files, 1983-1984 (Box 60)
  - House Committee on the Budget, 100th Congress, 1987-1988 (Box 61)
    - Vol. I-II, Hearings
    - Vol. III-IV, Task Force Hearings
    - Vol. V Ad Hoc Task Force Hearings
    - Vol VI, Committee Prints
    - Vol VII-VIII, Reports
    - Vol IX, Committee Prints
  - Correspondence, 1984-1985 (Box 62)
    - Aa - Ah
    - Ai - An
    - Ao - Az
    - Ba
    - Bb - Be
    - Bf - Bi
    - Bj - Bo
    - Br
    - Bs - Bz
    - Ca
    - Cb - Cn
    - Co - Cq
    - Cr - Cz
    - Da - Dh
    - Do - Dz
    - He - Hn
    - Ho - Hs
  - Correspondence (carbon copies, arranged by date of NLJ response), 1983 (Box 63)
    - January 8 - 14
    - January 17 - 21
    - January 22 - 28
    - Janaury 29 - February 4
    - February 5 - 11
    - February 12 - 18
    - February 19 - 25
    - February 26 - March 4
    - March 5 - 11
    - March 12 - 18
    - March 19 - 25
    - March 26 - April 1
    - April 2 - 8
    - April 9 - 15
    - April 16 - 22
    - April 23 - 29
    - April 30 - May 6
    - May 7 - 13
    - May 14 - 20
    - May 21 - 27
    - May 28 - June 3
    - June 4 - 10
    - June 11 - 17
    - June 18 - 24
    - June 25 - July 1
    - July 2 - 8
    - July 9 - 15
    - July 16 - 22
    - July 23 - 29
    - July 30 - August 5
    - August 6 - 12
    - August 13 - 19
    - August 20 - 26
    - August 27 - September 2
    - September 3 - 9
    - September 10 - 16
    - September 17 - 23
    - September 24 - 30
    - October 1 - 7
    - October 8 - 14
    - October 15 - 21
    - October 22 - 28
    - October 29 - November 4
    - November 6 - 15
    - November 16 - 24
  - Staff files, 1986-2006 (Box 64)
    - Mental Health Parity
    - Central America
    - Iran-Contra Affair
    - Central American Peace Talks
    - Central America visit
    - Roger Miranda "Central America"
    - Central America clippings
    - The Challenge to Democracy in Central America
    - U.S. Foreign POoicy and USSR
    - Member Preference letters
    - H.R. 4954 Member requests
    - School construction
    - CAFTA
    - Low Income Housing Tax Credit
    - Ball Bearings Caucus
    - Brownfields Reinvestment
    - Ways and Means markup, Budget reconciliation
    - Employee Stock Ownership Plans (ESOP), 109th Congress
    - Inversions, Stanley Works
    - Conservation donation
    - Conservation/Land Trust
    - Trade: Country of origin/Stanley
    - Ways and Means Hearing: US- Peru Trade agreement
    - Ways and Means Mark up: US-Oman Free Trade Agreement
    - Ways and Means Mark up: H.R. 1631, Ride 21
    - Ways and Means Hearing: President's Budget
    - Latin America Briefing, World Trade Organization mark up
    - Joint Committee on Taxation, organizational meeting
    - Ways and Means Hearing: Budget
    - Fuel Cell Tax Credit
  - Correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 65)
    - Do - Dz
    - E
    - Fa - Fra
    - Fre - Fz
    - Ga - Gat
    - Gau - Geo
    - Ger - Gi
    - Gl - Gree
    - Gref - Gz
    - Ha - Harel
  - Votes and Bills, 1986 (Box 66)
  - Veterans, undated (Box 67)
  - HR, 1983-1985 (Box 68)
  - Issues, undated, 1977-1987 (Box 69)
    - Connecticut Alcohol and Drug Abuse Commission
    - Fairness (includes major federal social programs)
    - NLJ Voting Record/Cosponsor list
    - American Public Welfare Association, Investing in Poor Families and their Children
    - Prospectus of Working Women's Concerens, Subcommittee on Employment Opportunities
    - Healthy Children; A program to Encourage the Development of Children's Health Services
    - Behavioral Sciences Institute, Overview of the Homebuilder Program
    - Shelter-Abused Women
    - Abortion--Right to Life
    - House Bills
    - Budget
    - Women's Issues
  - A - F Files, undated (Box 70)
  - Issues, Bills, Acts, etc.Files, undated, 1980-1988 (Box 72)
    - Nancy Johnson provisions, welfare reform
    - Welfare reform--100th Congress
    - Old Welfare reform (NLJ sponsored)
    - Press--NLJ and welfare reform
    - Gasper/Title X Rescinsion
    - Fair Housing Amendments
    - EEOC/Sexual Harassment
    - Civil Rights Commission
    - Retirement Equity Act
    - Dan Coats, Family Leave
    - Parental leave (anti)
    - Parental leave
    - Military Families
    - Missing Children
    - NLJ Career Conferences
    - Fair Insurance Practices Act
    - For future "Handicapped Fair"
    - PPFA v. AID
    - Coalition for Population and Development
    - H.R. 1170--Informed Consent
    - Civil Rights Restoration Act of 1987
    - Discrimination
    - EEA letter--Women's Caucus
    - CYF--Economic Security Task Force
    - Domestic Violence
    - Child Labor
    - Child Pornography
    - White House: Gender Gap
    - Newt Gingrich, Women's group
    - Group of Eight
    - 100th Congress Voting Records
    - Horvath Medicaid Case
    - Waterbury Child Guidance Clinic
    - Hublein Day Care Center
  - Voting Record, 99th Congress, undated (Box 73)
  - Votes and Bills, 1984 (Box 74)
  - Form letters--Issues, 1985-1988 (Box 75)
    - Federal Executive Pay Raise
    - Overtime Pay for Federal Employees
    - Federal Employees Pay
    - Bilingual Education
    - English Language Amendment
    - Informed Consent "Thanks"
    - Private Express Statutes--Pro
    - Reproductive Health Equity Act (update)
    - Anti-AIDS
    - AIDS and the Budget
    - Pro Title X
    - Medicare for Breast Cancer Screening
    - Immuno-Augmentation Therapy Evaluation
    - Drug Abuse--Anti
    - Childhood Immunization Program
    - Day Care Interest Groups
    - Preventive Health Services Block Grant
    - Compassionate Pain Relief Act
    - Hyde-Humphrey Human Life Bill
    - Dietary Services (Nursing Facilities)
    - Humane and Dignified Death Act
    - Medicare Quality Rules
    - March for Life
    - Visiting Nurses Associations memo
    - Third World and Women, Infants and Children Program
    - Senior Centers and Catastrophic (Medicare Catastrophic Protection Act)
    - Hospital Administrators "Thanks"
    - Hospital Administrators "No Comment"
    - Medicare Catastrophic Protection Act Financing
    - Lupus Awareness Month Reception
    - ERA--Anti
    - Civil Rights Restoration--Anti
    - Immigration and Naturalization Service and Employment Agencies
    - Volunteer Protection Act--Pro
    - Civil Rights Act (update)--Pro
    - Irish Immigration
    - Child Labor
    - Hatch-Johnson Child Care Bill "Dear Colleague"
    - Medicare Part B Increase
    - Social Security "Notch": Request for committee hearings
    - One-Year Head Start
    - AuPair America
  - Schedules and Invitations, 1983-1984 (Box 76)
  - Congressional Quarterly Vote, 1983 June - October (Box 77)